Guide to Voices of Crown Heights oral histories 2016.027
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Voices of Crown Heights oral histories: Brooklyn Historical Society, 2016-2017; 2016.027.1
  - Juravich, Nick, 2017 May 18; 2016.027.1.13
    Thirty-three years old at the time of the 2017 interview, Nick Juravich was born in Northampton, Massachusetts. His family is White, from German, Scottish, and Polish stock. His father is a professor of Labor Studies and his mother is a local historian. They live in Amherst, Massachusetts, where Juravich also lived from the age of nine. He went to the University of Chicago as an undergraduate, majoring in Urban History. He then received a Rhodes scholarship and worked on his master's degree at Oxford. After England, Juravich moved to New York City to be with his girlfriend; they found an apartment on Dean Street in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn and, later married, they were still living there in 2017. He started the blog "I Love Franklin Ave." in 2008 and wrote it for five years. He was actively involved with the Crow Hill Community Association from 2009 to 2013. Juravich was finishing his doctorate in New York City history at Columbia when the interview occurred.
    Nick Juravich begins the interview by describing his childhood homes and being raised as a "city kid" by an academic and a historian. Juravich remembers growing up in support of various forms of protests and growing into an anti-war activist while studying social and oral history as a University of Chicago undergraduate. He recalls his time at Oxford as a Rhodes Scholar and returning to the States to find work and a home with his wife in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. Making a living as an after-school coordinator with the New York Road Runners, Juravich describes the footwork and encounters that gave him a deep experience of Brooklyn neighborhoods, shop owners, and residents. Settling into a reflection on life in his building, the surrounding block of brownstones on Dean Street between Franklin and Bedford, and the businesses of Crown Heights, he relates how his blog emerged and became a document of and public forum for the community. Much of the latter part of the interview is spent sharing tales of controversies amid businesses, residents, public services, and community groups, and analyzing the dramatic arc of gentrification and how and when it runs its course in Crown Heights. Interview conducted by Svetlana Kitto.
    Activism; Bars (Drinking establishments) |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Economic conditions |y 21st century; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions |y 21st century; Business enterprises |x African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community activists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Eastern Parkway (New York, N.Y.); Franklin Avenue (Brooklyn, N.Y.); Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Historic preservation |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Multiculturalism; Police brutality |z United States; Police-community relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Racism |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Restaurants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Tenants' associations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Zoning -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Crow Hill Community Association (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Crown Heights Tenant Union (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Esquilin, Frank; Juravich, Nicholas A.; New York (N.Y.). Police Department; Porter, Evangeline; West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
  - La'Viticus, Timothy, 2017 July 13; 2016.027.1.18
    Timothy La'Viticus was born in Virginia, but has lived in the Bronx most of his life. He was born Timothy Boyd, but prefers to use La'Viticus, as he is from the ballroom scene in New York Black gay culture, from the house of La'Viticus. He has worked managing gay bars and clubs in the Greenwich Village neighborhood of Manhattan and in Brooklyn, and once a month he hosts a performance for young gay and drag artists. He is a retired home care worker, and has offered his services to his friends and family; the elders of the lesbian, gay, bisexual, transgender Black and Latino scene.
    In this interview, Timothy La'Viticus talks about his involvement at the tail end of the Starlite Lounge's existence in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. The Starlite was one of the oldest city bars to welcome gay, as well as heterosexual, patrons. La'Viticus recalls other gay clubs in the city which have closed, including Two Potatoes/ Chances Are on Christopher Street in the Greenwich Village neighborhood of Manhattan. He relates his experiences of dealing with the new owners of the building which housed the Starlite Lounge, and the reasons why Starlite ultimately closed. La'Viticus also shares some of his biographical background. Throughout, he fondly describes the people who worked alongside him in the bars, as well as patrons; a few specifically and otherwise generally. Interview conducted by Andrew Viñales.
    Bars (Drinking establishments) |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bronx (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social life and customs; Business enterprises |x African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community identity |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Gay culture |z New York (State) |z New York; Gays |x Social life and customs; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Greenwich Village (New York, N.Y.); Lesbians; Multiculturalism; Nightclubs |z New York (State) |z New York; Queer culture; Transgender people; Cuthbert, Donna; King, William (William "Butch" King); La'Viticus, Timothy; Starlite Lounge (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Two Potatoes (New York, N.Y.)
  - Law, Bob, 2016 December 21; 2016.027.1.05
    Bob Law is an African American man from the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. Nationally known as a radio broadcaster in Black media, he also owns a health and wellness store (originally located in the Prospect Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn on Vanderbilt Avenue, relocated to the border of Prospect Heights/Crown Heights on Atlantic Avenue) and previously owned a restaurant on Vanderbilt Avenue in Prospect Heights. He is also an activist; having served as a prominent member of the Congress of Racial Equality (CORE) in the 1960s, continuing in Black Nationalist and electoral politics in Brooklyn, and suing the Board of Education in the early 1990s for a White bias in teaching Black children. He grew up in the Kingsborough Houses, his parents coming from Georgia and South Carolina. At the time of the 2016 interview, he was seventy-seven years old.
    In this first of two interviews, Bob Law shares his memories of growing up in the Kingsborough Houses in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. Referring to his childhood, he describes the community as racially mixed, though predominantly White, with friendships existing across racial lines. Growing up working class, he shares that— along with middle class values that Black parents instilled in their children— he and his peers had easy access to fun and entertainment, including Ebbets Field and TV personalities, and thus never wanted for anything. Along with a description of gang culture in the area, he recounts local/area sports stars who both made it to the major league and those who did not, due to racism. He describes Crown Heights as a neighborhood where some Black people aspired to improve their lives and invest in a community. Law speaks about Blacks entering electoral politics in Brooklyn; beginning with Maude Richardson and her run for state assembly, to Shirley Chisolm, to present day politicians like Leticia James. He talks about Brooklyn CORE, for which he was a central member, and their integrationist platform. Law also speaks about his shifting Black consciousness; being inspired by Malcolm X and a turning point of the church bombing in Alabama where four Black girls were killed. He also speaks about jazz venues in Brooklyn. Interview conducted by Amaka Okechukwu.
    Baseball |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Black nationalism |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Blacks |x Race identity; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Politics and government; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 20th century; Children |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Civil rights movements |z United States |y 20th century; Community activists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community centers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Games |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gangs |z New York (State) |z Kings Country; Harlem (New York, N.Y.); Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; March on Washington for Jobs and Freedom, Washington, D.C., 1963; Nightclubs |z New York (State) |z New York; Popular music |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z United States; Racism |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Working class |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Chisholm, Shirley; Congress of Racial Equality. Brooklyn Chapter; Dubrow's Cafeteria (New York, N.Y.); King, Martin Luther, Jr., 1929-1968; Kingsborough Houses (Housing complex); Law, Bob; Richardson, Maude; X, Malcolm, 1925-1965
  - Law, Bob, 2017 January 22; 2016.027.1.06
    Bob Law is an African American man from the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. Nationally known as a radio broadcaster in Black media, he also owns a health and wellness store (originally located in the Prospect Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn on Vanderbilt Avenue, relocated to the border of Prospect Heights/Crown Heights on Atlantic Avenue) and previously owned a restaurant on Vanderbilt Avenue in Prospect Heights. He is also an activist; having served as a prominent member of the Congress of Racial Equality (CORE) in the 1960s, continuing in Black Nationalist and electoral politics in Brooklyn, and suing the Board of Education in the early 1990s for a White bias in teaching Black children. He grew up in the Kingsborough Houses, his parents coming from Georgia and South Carolina. At the time of the 2017 interview, he was seventy-seven years old.
    In the second of two interviews, Bob Law recounts his entry into radio and speaks about the role of Black radio in energizing Black political activity in Brooklyn and across the nation. He describes the emergence of the Black United Front and distinguishes between the Brooklyn CORE mobilizations in the 1960s and the police brutality protests in the late 1970s (particularly the 1978 Eastern Parkway protest of Arthur Miller's killing). He points out that the anger of the 1970s protests was a significant contrast to the "politics of respectability" in the 1960s protests. Law speaks at length about electoral politics in Brooklyn, highlighting his work on Al Vann's early campaigns and his thoughts about Shirley Chisolm's role in the community. He recalls a lawsuit that he organized against the Department of Education in 1990 and his role in organizing the Al-Karim School decades prior. Law also speaks about his experience with housing in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn and his thoughts about its future. Interview conducted by Amaka Okechukwu.
    African Americans -- United States; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Politics and government; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social life and customs; Civil rights movements |z United States |y 20th century; Community activists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Education |z New York (State) |z New York; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Million Man March (1995: Washington, D.C.); New York (N.Y.); Police brutality |z United States; Police-community relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Prospect Heights (New York, N.Y.); Race relations |z United States; Racism |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Radio; Radio talk shows -- United States; Television talk shows -- United States; Al-Karim School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Chisholm, Shirley; Daughtry, Herbert, 1931-; Dinkins, David N.; Evans, Randolph; Jackson, Jesse; Miller, Arthur, Jr.; Law, Bob; National Black United Front; New York (N.Y.). Police Department; Uhuru Sasa School; Vann, Albert; WBLS (Radio Station: New York, N.Y.); WWRL (Radio station: New York, N.Y.)
  - Lesold, Constance, 2017 April 7; 2016.027.1.10
    Constance "Connie" Lesold was born in North Carolina in 1938. Lesold attended the University of North Carolina, Greensboro (when it was a women's college) and moved to New York City after graduation in 1961. She first visited the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights in 1966 and had an apartment at 225 Eastern Parkway with her husband, Helmuth Lesold, by 1967. The couple had one son who was born in 1970. A social worker until retirement as well as an engaged community member and activist, she was president of the Parkway Independent Democrats and an official of Community Board Eight. Along with her husband, several Brooklyn community boards, the Brooklyn Botanic Garden, and a public coalition, she opposed the Metropolitan Transportation Authority's move to end service on the Franklin Avenue Shuttle. Lesold also served on boards of organizations and daycares, and in leadership in the Eastern Parkway Coalition for many years. A widow since 1994, she also volunteered with the Brooklyn Mental Hygiene Court Monitors Project.
    In the interview, Constance Lesold talks about her many memories of the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. She discusses her longtime residence of thirty years at an apartment building on Eastern Parkway. She focuses on the battle to save the Franklin Avenue Shuttle from permanent closure. Throughout she names other activists, community leaders and organizations, and politicians; these include her husband, Community Boards Eight and Nine, Borough President Howard Golden, Arthur Miller, the Brooklyn Museum, New Muse, and the Children's Museum. Lesold chronicles the politics affecting social issues in Brooklyn, often referencing the Eastern Parkway Coalition Garden above the Franklin Avenue Shuttle. The gentrification of Crown Heights, tenants associations and how neighbors run their buildings, and justice for those with mental health issues are other concerns for Lesold. She concludes by contemplating Vermont, where she'll be living next. Constance Lesold was also recorded for the Listen to this: Crown Heights Oral History collection in 2010 (2010.020) and she made a gift of the Eastern Parkway Coalition records, 1952-2007 (2007.016) to BHS. Interview conducted by Amaka Okechukwu.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Community activists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community gardens |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Eastern Parkway (New York, N.Y.); Environmentalism |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Franklin Avenue (Brooklyn, N.Y.); Gangs |z New York (State) |z Kings Country; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Local transit |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Social justice |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Subway stations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Subways |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Tenants' associations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Urban beautification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn Mental Hygiene Court Monitors Project; Brooklyn Museum; Carthan, Hattie; Community Board No. 8 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Eastern Parkway Coalition; Lesold, Constance; Lesold, Helmuth; Muse Community Museum (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); New York (N.Y.). Police Department; New York (State). Metropolitan Transit Authority.; Richmond, Frederick W., 1923-
  - Lewis, Sylvia Wong, 2017 June 26; 2016.027.1.24
    Born Sylvia Elaine Smith in Harlem in 1952, Sylvia Wong Lewis moved to the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights when she was two years old. Her father was African American, originally from Ocean Springs, Mississippi; and her mother, whose maiden name was "Wong," was Chinese Trinidadian. Her paternal grandmother was Madame Tempy Smith, a music teacher who led Sylvia's aunts and uncles in a traveling musical and dance troop. When Lewis's family moved to Crown Heights, her grandmother already lived there, in a house located very near the Lubavitch headquarters at 770 Eastern Parkway. Sylvia's own family lived on President Street, a few blocks from that part of President called "doctors row"—known for its large houses and doctor's offices. She attended St. Matthew's, a Catholic school, and then Wingate High School, from which she graduated in 1969. After high school she matriculated to Smith College. Upon graduating from college, she worked as a journalist, educator, and media professional. She has completed two films—"Healing Games" and "From Shanghai to Harlem," which documents her mother's heritage and family.
    In this interview, Sylvia Wong Lewis talks about growing up as a child of blue collar Caribbean and African-American parents living on a block in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn that was middle class and racially integrated in the 1950s and 1960s. Her father worked as a baker, and her mother operated a daycare out of the family home, often caring for the children of local teachers. She describes her upbringing as multicultural: she attended St. Matthew's Catholic school, participated in the Girl Scouts troop at First African Methodist Episcopal Zion Church, and often accompanied her Chinese grandmother to a Buddhist temple in Chinatown. She also talks about the neighborhood's geography, and what it was like to cross over into the northern side of Eastern Parkway— regarded by some longtime residents as the border between Crown Heights and the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn. Recalling that her grandmother lived "behind" the Lubavitchers' main synagogue, Lewis recounts her interactions with both Hasidic and non-Hasidic Jews in the neighborhood. She speaks of being fearful of the Maccabees, a Hasidic security patrol, because the patrol's efforts to keep the neighborhood safe often targeted Black people. She also recalls an incident where the police stopped and frisked her two younger brothers in front of their mother, an event that traumatized her. Another key theme in the interview is Lewis's class consciousness as a working class kid encountering members of New York's Black elite that had been living in Crown Heights. She mentions meeting Jackie Robinson's wife, as well babysitting for an associate of Lena Horne. She talks about her experiences during the blackout of 1977, as well as the 1991 unrest, and the changes in the neighborhood she witnessed since growing up there. After recording, Lewis requested that some biographically related details be removed. Under two minutes near the ninety-nine minute mark have been edited from the audio. Interview conducted by Zaheer Ali.
    African Americans |x Relations with Jews; African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Demonstration Cities Program (New York, N.Y.); Family life -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Games |x Street |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Harlem (New York, N.Y.); Hasidim |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Police-community relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; School children |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Social classes |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Trinidadian Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Congregation Lubavitch (Crown Heights, New York, N.Y.); George W. Wingate High School; Girl Scouts of the United States of America; Lewis, Sylvia Wong; Maccabee Security Guard Services (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Pointer, Louvenia; Smith, Tempy, Madame; St. Matthew's School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); United States. Model Cities Administration
  - Lightstone, Mordechai, 2016 December 15; 2016.027.1.04
    Biographical / Historical
    Mordechai Lightstone was born Jonathan Samuel Lightstone in 1984 in Los Angeles, and grew up in a Jewish family that attended a Reform synagogue. As he grew in his religious observance of his faith's tradition, especially through his involvement in the Hasidic community, he identified more closely with one of his given Hebrew names—Mordechai, the name of one of his great-grandfathers. He first visited the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn in 1998 or 1999, with his uncle, as part of a trip to visit the Lubavitch Hasidic headquarters. Less than a decade later in 2007, he moved to Crown Heights to study, and became a rabbi and emissary for the Chabad community. An active writer and social media presence, he now serves as Director of Social Media and Features Editor for Lubavitch.com, the official website for Chabad-Lubavitch World Headquarters.
    In this interview Mordechai Lightstone talks about the role the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn played in the evolution of his Jewish identity and deepening of his faith. He recalls the first time he ever heard of Crown Heights in a radio broadcast about the 1991 unrest, which he remembers causing his mother great sadness. He recounts being introduced to the Lubavitch community by his uncle while visiting Montreal. It was while accompanying his uncle that Lightstone first visited Crown Heights, around the age of fourteen. He describes visiting the resting place of the Rebbe, the spiritual leader of the Lubavitch; and gives his first impressions of the Chabad headquarters at 770 Eastern Parkway and rituals that he found both strange at first but spiritually compelling. He reflects on his growing sense of commitment to Judaism after his return to Los Angeles, and his gradual identification with the Chabad community. He recalls some of the mentors in the community that helped guide his learning and development, and his decision to move to Crown Heights in 2007. In his remembrance of his first years in Crown Heights, he talks about studying, his training as a meat slaughterer, and courtship and marriage. He describes his family's journey to home-ownership in Crown Heights, addresses perceptions of the role of Jews in neighborhood real estate, and how gentrification and housing pressures have impacted members of the Jewish community. One of the central themes of his interview is the geography of Crown Heights—its meaning, its identity, and its boundaries; and how that geography is inextricably tied to the neighborhood's (and his) Jewish history. Interview conducted by Zaheer Ali.